Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, World War II is now over
and the end of this war will see the
rise of two major global superpowers,
the Soviet Union and the United States.
The thing is, these two superpowers were
allies during World War II and pretty
much immediately after the war their
alliance collapses. The reason for this
is pretty simple, these two countries'
ideologies are completely different.
[music]
Over in the US, we have democracy,
capitalism, and free markets. However,
going over to the Soviet Union, we now
have a system known as authoritarian
communism, which means the state
controls literally everything. So, you
might think that these two countries are
going to go to war, but the world just
went through a horribly devastating war
and now things like nuclear weapons
exist. If another war were to happen,
it's not unreasonable to say that the
world could quite literally come to an
end. So, the thing that emerges, the
Cold War, isn't a normal war at all. It
will be a 45-year long series of smaller
conflicts and tensions that, over time,
add up to one massive, quote, Cold War.
So, from 1945 to 1981 thing will remain
constant, containment. Simply meaning
that the US's goal [music] is to stop
communism from spreading. This idea
comes from George Kennan's Long
Telegram, where he argues that the
Soviet Union will expand unless firmly
contained. So, let's give some examples
of this containment. First is economic
aid. The Truman Doctrine will be made,
declaring the US will give money to
Greece and Turkey to stop communist
influence. Also, the Marshall Plan will
be enacted to send billions of dollars
to rebuild Western Europe after the war.
But, the second thing here is military
alliances. Western democracies will ally
under the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization, or NATO, and later the
Soviet Union will respond and create the
Warsaw Pact for all of its countries.
And now notice that with these new
organizations, the world is essentially
split in half. Finally, the last thing
here will be military conflicts. This is
where we see proxy wars like the Korean
War and looking at this, basically North
Korea is communist and wants to invade
the democratic South Korea. The US will
ally with the South, the communist China
will ally with the North, and the war
happens, and after 3 years it will end
in a draw. Cool. Then the Cuban Missile
Crisis will have the Soviets place
nuclear missiles in Cuba, the US
blockades Cuba, the world nearly ends,
but all is good after some negotiation.
But by the 1970s, this Cold War had
really gone on for long enough. Vietnam
is something that we'll cover later in
this unit, but let's just say that the
US was not having a great time in
Vietnam. Under Nixon, various treaties
and open communications between the US
and China / the Soviet Union will
happen. And the key method of the Cold
War will now turn to something called
detente, meaning to ease tensions. There
are also so many other parts to this
Cold War that I do not have time to go
over. Just understand that the US used a
lot of different strategies over the
years to manage the Soviet threat. On
the screen now are AP-style questions
for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.